So I want to do two things, talk about
Talk a little bit about like some ways to use Convolutional Nets in various ways
Which I haven't gone through last time
and
And I'll also
Talk about different types of architectures that
Some of which are very recently designed
that people have been
Kind of playing with for quite a while. So let's see
So last time when we talked about Convolutional Nets we stopped that the
idea that we can use Convolutional Nets with kind of a sliding we do over large images and it consists in just
applying the convolution on large images
which is a very general image, a very general method, so we're gonna
See a few more things on how to use convolutional Nets and
to some extent
I'm going to
Rely on a bit of sort of historical papers and things like this to explain kind of simple forms of all of those ideas
so as I said last time
I had this example where there's multiple characters on an image and you can, you have a convolutional net that
whose output is also a convolution like everyday air is a convolution so you can interpret the output as
basically giving you a score for every category and for every window on the input and the the framing of the window depends on
Like the the windows that the system observes when your back project for my particular output
Kind of steps by the amount of subsampling the total amount of sub something you have in a network
So if you have two layers that subsample by a factor of two, you have two pooling layers, for example
That's a factor of two the overall
subsampling ratio is 4 and what that means is that every output is
Gonna basically look at a window on the input and successive outputs is going to look at the windows that are separated by four pixels
Okay, it's just a product of all the subsampling layers
So
this this is nice, but then you're gonna have to make sense of
All the stuff that's on the input. How do you pick out objects objects that
overlap each other
Etc. And one thing you can do for this is called "Non maximum suppression"
Which is what people use in sort of object detection
so basically what that consists in is that if you have
Outputs that kind of are more or less at the same place and
or also like overlapping places and one of them tells you I see a
Bear and the other one tells you I see a horse one of them wins
Okay, it's probably one that's wrong. And you can't have a bear on a horse at the same time at the same place
So you do what's called? No, maximum suppression you can
Look at which
which of those has the highest score and you kind of pick that one or you see if
any neighbors also recognize that as a bear or a horse and you kind of make a
vote if you want, a local vote, okay, and I'm gonna go to the details of this because
Just just kind of rough ideas. Well, this is
already implemented in code that you can download and also it's kind of the topic of a
full-fledged computer vision course
So here we just allude to kind of how we use deep learning for this kind of application
Let's see, so here's
Again going back to history a little bit some ideas of how you use
neural nets to or convolutional nets in this case to
Recognize strings of characters which is kind of the same program as recognizing multiple objects, really
So if you have, you have an image that contains the image at the top... "two, three two, zero, six"
It's a zip code and the characters touch so you don't know how to separate them in advance
So you just apply a convolutional net to the entire string but you don't know in advance what width the characters will take and so
what you see here are four different sets of outputs and those four different sets of outputs of
the convolutional net
Each of which has ten rows and the ten words corresponds to each of the ten categories
so if you look at the top for example the top, the top block
the white squares represent high-scoring categories
So what you see on the left is that the number two is being recognized. So the window that is looked at by the
Output units that are on the first column is on the, on the left side of the image and it, and it detects a two
Because the you know their order 0 1 2 3 4 etc
So you see a white square that corresponds to the detection of a 2
and then as the window is
shifted over the, over the input
Is a 3 or low scoring 3 that is seen then the 2 again there's three character
It's three detectors that see this 2 and then nothing then the 0 and then the 6
Now this first
System looks at a fairly narrow window and
Or maybe it's a wide window no, I think it's a wide window so it looks at a pretty wide window and
it
when it looks at the, the
The two, the two that's on the left for example, it actually sees a piece of the three with it, with it
So it's kind of in the window the different sets of outputs here correspond to different size
Of the kernel of the last layer. So the second row the second block
The the size of the kernel is four in the horizontal dimension
The next one is 3 and the next one is 2. what this allows the system to do is look at
Regions of various width on the input without being kind of too confused by the characters that are on the side if you want
so for example
the, the, the second to the zero is very high-scoring on the, on the, the
Second third and fourth map but not very high-scoring on the top map. Similarly, the three is kind of high-scoring on the
second third and fourth map
but not on the first map because the three kind of overlaps with the two and so
It wants to really look at in our window to be able to recognize it
Okay. Yes
So it's the size of the white square that indicates the score basically, okay
So look at you know, this this column here you have a high-scoring zero
Here because it's the first the first row correspond to the category zero
but it's not so high-scoring from the top, the top one because that
output unit looks at a pretty wide input and it gets confused by the stuff that's on the side
Okay, so you have something like this
so now you have to make sense out of it and extract the best interpretation of that, of that sequence and
It's true for zip code, but it's true for just about every piece of text. Not every combination of characters is possible
so when you read English text there is, you know, an English dictionary English grammar and
Not every combination of character is possible so you can have a language model that
attempts to
Tell you what is the most likely sequence of characters. So we're looking at here given that this is English or whatever language
Or given that this is a zip code not every zip code are possible. So this --- possibility for error correction
So how do we take that into account? I'll come to this in a second but
But here what we need to do is kind of you know
Come up with a consistent interpretation
That you know, there's obviously a three there's obviously a two, a three,a zero somewhere
Another two etc. How to return this
array of scores into, into a consistent
interpretation
Is the width of the, the horizontal width of the,
the kernel of the last layer
Okay
Which means when you backprop---, back project on the input the, the viewing window on the input that influences that particular unit
has various size depending on which unit you look at. Yes
The width of the block yeah
It's a, it corresponds
it's how wide the
Input image is divided by 4 because the substantive issue is 4 so you get one of one column of those for every four pixel
so remember we had this, this way of using a neural net, convolutional net which is that you, you basically make every
Convolution larger and you view the last layer as a convolution as well. And now what you get is multiple
Outputs. Okay. So what I'm representing here on the slide you just saw
is the, is this 2d array on the output which corresponds where, where the, the row corresponds to categories
Okay, and each column corresponds to a different location on the input
And I showed you those examples here so
Here, this is a different representation here where the, the character that is displayed just before the title bar is you know
Indicates the winning category, so I'm not displaying the scores of every category. I'm just, just, just displaying the winning category here
but each
Output looks at a 32 by 32 window and the next output by looks at a 32 by 32 window shifted by 4 pixels
Ok, etc.
So how do you turn this you know sequence of characters into the fact that it is either 3 5 or 5 3
Ok, so here the reason why we have four of those is so that is because the last player
this different
Is different last layers, if you want this four different last layers each of which is trained to recognize the ten categories
And those last layers have different kernel width so they essentially look at different width of Windows on the input
So you want some that look at wide windows so they can they can recognize kind of large characters and some that look at, look
At narrow windows so they can recognize narrow characters without being
perturbed by the the neighboring characters
So if you know a priori that there are five five characters here because it's a zip code
You can do you can use a trick and
There is sort of few specific tricks that
I can explain but I'm going to explain sort of the general trick if you want. I
Didn't want to talk about this actually at least not now
Okay here so here's a general trick the general trick is or the you know, kind of a somewhat specific trick
Oops, I don't know way it keeps changing slide
You say I have I know I have five characters in this word, is there a
So that's one of those arrays that produces scores so for each category
Let's say I have four categories here and each location
There's a score, okay and let's say I know that I want five characters out
I'm gonna draw them vertically one two, three, four five because it's a zip code
So the question I'm going to ask now is what is the best character I can put in this and
In this slot in the first slot
And the way I'm going to do this is I'm gonna draw an array
And on this array
I'm going to say what's the score here for, at every intersection in the array?
It's gonna be, what is the, what is the score of putting
A particular character here at that location given the score that I have at the output of my neural net
Okay, so let's say that
So what I'm gonna have to decide is since I have fewer characters
On the on the output to the system five
Then I have viewing windows and scores produced by the by the system. I'm gonna have to figure out which one I drop
okay, and
What I can do is build this, build this array
And
What I need to do is go from here to here by finding a path through this through this array
In such a way that I have exactly five
Steps if you want, so each step corresponds to to a character and
the overall score of a particular string is the overall is the sum of all the scores that
Are along this path in other words if I get
Three
Instances here, three locations where I have a high score for this particular category, which is category one. Okay let's call it 0
So 1 2 3
I'm gonna say this is the same guy and it's a 1
and here if I have
Two guys. I have high score for 3, I'm gonna say those are the 3 and here
I have only one guy that has high score for 2. So that's a 2 etc
So
This path here has to be sort of continuous
I can't jump from one position to another because that would be kind of breaking the order of the characters. Okay?
And I need to find a path that goes through high-scoring cells if you want that correspond to
High scoring categories along this path and it's a way of
saying you know if I have
if those three cells here or
Give me the same character. It's only one character. I'm just going to output
One here that corresponds to this
Ok, those three guys have high score. I stay on the one, on the one and then I transition
To the second character. So now I'm going to fill out this slot and this guy has high score for three
So I'm going to put three here and this guy has a high score for two
as two
Etc
The principle to find this this path is a shortest path algorithm
You can think of this as a graph where I can go from the lower left cell to the upper right cell
By either going to the left
or going up and to the left and
For each of those transitions there is a there's a cost and for each of the
For putting a character at that location, there is also a cost or a score if you want
So the overall
Score of the one at the bottom would be the combined score of the three locations that detect that one and
Because it's more all three of them are
contributing evidence to the fact that there is a 1
When you constrain the path to have 5 steps
Ok, it has to go from the bottom left to the top right and
It has 5 steps, so it has to go through 5 steps
There's no choice. That's that's how you force the system to kind of give you 5 characters basically, right?
And because the path can only go from left to right and from top to bottom
It has to give you the characters in the order in which they appear in the image
So it's a way of imposing the order of the character and imposing that there are fives, there are five characters in the string. Yes
Yes, okay in the back, yes, right. Yes
Well, so if we have just the string of one you have to have
Trained the system in advance so that when it's in between two ones or two characters, whatever they are, it says nothing
it says none of the above
Otherwise you can tell, right
Yeah, a system like this needs to be able to tell you this is none of the above. It's not a character
It's a piece of it or I'm in the middle of two characters or I have two characters on the side
But nothing in the middle
Yeah, absolutely
It's a form of non maximum suppression
so you can think of this as kind of a smart form of non maximum suppression where you say like for every location you can only
have one
character
And the order in which you produce the five characters must correspond to the order in which they appear on the image
What you don't know is how to warp one into the other. Okay. So how to kind of you know, how many
detectors are gonna see the number two. It may be three of them and we're gonna decide they're all the same
So the thing is for all of you who
are on computer science, which is not everyone
The the way you compute this path is just a shortest path algorithm. You do this with dynamic programming
Okay
so find the shortest path to go from bottom left to top right by going through by only going to
only taking transition to the right or diagonally and
by minimizing the
cost so if you think each of those
Is is filled by a cost or maximizing the score if you think that scores there are probabilities, for example
And it's just a shortest path algorithm in a graph
This kind of method by the way was
So many early methods of speech recognition kind of work this way, not with neural nets though. We sort of hand extracted features from
but it would basically match the sequence of vectors extracted from a speech signal to a template of a word and then you
know try to see how you warp the time to match the the
The word to be recognized to to the templates and you had a template for every word over fixed size
This was called DTW, dynamic time working. There's more sophisticated version of it called hidden markov models, but it's very similar
People still do this to some extent
Okay
So detection, so if you want to apply commercial net for detection
it works amazingly well, and it's surprisingly simple, but you
You know what you need to do
You basically need to let's say you wanna do face detection
Which is a very easy problem one of the first problems that computer vision started solving really well for kind of recognition
you collect a data set of
images with faces and images without faces and
you train a
convolutional net with input window in something like 20 by 20 or 30 by 30 pixels?
To tell you whether there is a face in it or not
Okay. Now you take this convolutional net, you apply it on an image and if there is a face that happens to be roughly
30 by 30 pixels the
the content will will light up at the corresponding output and
Not light up when there is no face
now there is two problems with this, the first problem is
there is many many ways a patch of an image can be a non face and
During your training, you probably haven't seen all of them. You haven't seen even a representative set of them
So your system is gonna have lots of false positives
That's the first problem. Second problem is in the picture not all faces are 30 by 30 pixels. So how do you handle
Size variation so one way to handle size variation, which is very simple
but it's mostly unnecessary in modern versions, well
at least it's not completely necessary
Is you do a multiscale approach. So you take your image you run your detector on it. It fires whenever it wants
And you will detect faces are small then you reduce the image by
Some scale in this case, in this case here
I take a square root of two
You apply the convolutional net again on that smaller image and now it's going to be able to detect faces that are
That were larger in the original image because now what was 30 by 30 pixel is now about 20 by 20 pixels, roughly
Okay
But there may be bigger faces there. So you scale the image again by a factor of square root of 2
So now the images the size of the original one and you run the convolutional net again
And now it's going to detect faces that were 60 by 60 pixels
In the original image, but are now 30 by 30 because you reduce the size by half
You might think that this is expensive but it's not. Tthe
expense is, half of the expense is the final scale
the sum of the expense of the other networks are
Combined is about the same as the final scale
It's because the size of the network is you know
Kind of the square of the the size of the image on one side
And so you scale down the image by square root of 2 the network you have to run is smaller by a factor of 2
Okay, so the overall cost of this is 1 plus 1/2 plus 1/4 plus 1/8 plus 1/16 etc
Which is 2 you waste a factor of 2 by doing multi scale, which is very small. Ok
you can afford a factor of 2 so
This is a completely ancient face detection system from the early 90s and
the maps that you see here are all kind of
maps that indicate kind of
Scores of face detectors, the face detector here I think is 20 by 20 pixels. So it's very low res and
It's a big mess at the fine scales. You see kind of high-scoring areas, but it's not really very definite
But you see more
More definite
Things down here. So here you see
A white blob here white blob here white blob here same here. You see white blob here, White blob here and
Those are faces
and so that's now how you, you need to do maximum suppression to get those
little red squares that are kind of the winning categories if you want the winning locations where you have a face
So
Known as sumo suppression in this case means I have a high-scoring white white blob here
That means there is probably the face underneath which is roughly 20 by 20
It is another face in a window of 20 by 20. That means one of those two is wrong
so I'm just gonna take the highest-scoring one within the window of 20 by 20 and
Suppress all the others and you'll suppress the others at that location at that scale
I mean that nearby location at that scale but also at other scales. Okay, so you you pick the highest-scoring
blob if you want
For every location every scale
And whenever you pick one you you suppress the other ones that could be conflicting with it either
because they are a different scale at the same place or
At the same scale, but you know nearby
Okay, so that's the
that's the first problem and the second problem is the fact that as I said, there's many ways to be different from your face and
Most likely your training set doesn't have all the non-faces, things that look like faces
So the way people deal with this is that they do what's called negative mining
so
You go through a large collection of images
when you know for a fact that there is no face and you run your detector and you keep all the
Patches where you detector fires
You verify that there is no faces in them and if there is no face you add them to your negative set
Okay, then you retrain your detector. And then you use your retrained detector to do the same
Go again through a large dataset of images where there you know
There is no face and whenever your detector fires add that as a negative sample
you do this four or five times and
In the end you have a very robust face detector that does not fall victim to negative samples
These are all things that look like faces in natural images are not faces
This works really well
This is over 15 years old work this is my grandparents marriage, their wedding
their wedding
Okay
So here's a another interesting use of convolutional nets and this is for
Semantic segmentation what's called semantic segmentation, I alluded to this in the first the first lecture
so what is semantic segmentation is the problem of assigning a category to every pixel in an image and
Every pixel will be labeled with a category of the object it belongs to
So imagine this would be very useful if you want to say drive a robot in nature. So this is a
Robotics project that I worked on, my students and I worked on a long time ago
And what you like is to label the image so that regions that the robot can drive on
are indicated and
Areas that are obstacles also indicated so the robot doesn't drive there. Okay
So here the green areas are things that the robot can drive on and the red areas are obstacles like tall grass in that case
So the way you you train a convolutional net to do to do this kind of semantic segmentation is very similar to what I just
Described you you take a patch from the image
In this case. I think the patches were
20 by 40 or something like that, they are actually small
For which, you know what the central pixel is whether it's traversable or not, whether it's green or red?
okay, either is being manually labeled or the label has been obtained in some way and
You run a conv net on this patch and you train it, you know
tell me if it's if he's green or red tell me if it's
Drivable area or not
And once the system is trained you apply it on the entire image and it you know
It puts green or red depending on where it is. in this particular case actually, there were five categories
There's the super green green purple, which is a foot of an object
Red, which is an obstacle that you know threw off and super red, which is like a definite obstacle
Over here. We're only showing three three colors now in this particular
Project the the labels were actually collected automatically you didn't have to manually
Label the images and the patches what we do would be to run the robot around and then
through stereo vision figure out if a pixel is a
Correspond to an object that sticks out of the ground or is on the ground
So the the middle column here it says stereo labels these are
Labels, so the color green or red is computed from stereo vision from basically 3d reconstruction
okay, so for, you have two cameras and
The two cameras can estimate the distance of every pixel by basically comparing patches. It's relatively expensive, but it kind of works
It's not completely reliable, but it sort of works
So now for every pixel you have a depth the distance from the camera
Which means you know the position of that pixel in 3d which means you know
If it sticks out out of the ground or if it's on the ground because you can fit a plane to the ground
okay, so the green pixels are the ones that are basically
You know near the ground and the red ones are the ones that are up
so now you have labels you can try and accomplish on that to
predict those labels
Then you will tell me why would you want to train a convolutional net on that to do this if you can do this from stereo?
And the answer is stereo only works up to ten meters, roughly
Past ten meters you can't really using binocular vision and stereo vision, you can't really estimate the distance very well
And so that only works out to about ten meters and driving a robot by only looking
ten meters ahead of you is not a good idea
It's like driving a car in the fog right? It's gonna it's not very efficient
So what you used to accomplished on that for is to label every pixel in the image up to the horizon
essentially
Okay, so the cool thing about about this system is that as I said the labels were collected automatically but also
The robot
Adapted itself as it run because he collects stereo labels constantly
It can constantly retrain its neural net to adapt to the environment
it's in. In this particular instance of this robot, it would only will only retrain the last layer
So the N minus 1 layers of the ConvNet were fixed, were trained in the in the lab
And then the last layer was kind of adapted as the robot run, it allowed the robot to deal with environments
He'd never seen before
essentially
You still have long-range vision?
The input to the the conv network basically multiscale views of sort of bands of the image around the horizon
no need to go into details
Is a very small neural net by today's standard but that's what we could afford I
Have a video. I'm not sure it's gonna work, but I'll try
Yeah, it works
So I should tell you a little bit about the castor character he characters here so
Huh
You don't want the audio
So Pierre Semanet and Raia Hadsell were two students
working with me on this project two PhD students
Pierre Sermanet is at Google Brain. He works on robotics and Raia Hadsell is the sales director of Robotics at DeepMind
Marco Scoffier is NVIDIA
Matt Grimes is a DeepMind, Jan Ben is at Mobile Eye which is now Intel
Ayse Erkan is at
Twitter and
Urs Muller is still working with us, he is
Actually head of a big group that works on autonomous driving at Nvidia and he is collaborating with us
Actually
Our further works on this project, so this is a robot
And it can drive it about you know, sort of fast walking speed
And it's supposed to drive itself in sort of nature
So it's got this mass with four eyes, there are two stereo pairs to two stereo camera pairs and
It has three computers in the belly. So it's completely autonomous. It doesn't talk to the network or anything
And those those three computers
I'm on the left. That's when I had a pony tail
Okay, so here the the system is the the neural net is crippled so the we didn't turn on the neural Nets
It's only using stereo vision and now it's using the neural net
so it's it's pretty far away from this barrier, but it sees it and so it directly goes to
The side it wants to go to a goal, a GPS coordinate. That's behind it. Same here
He wants to go to a GPS coordinate behind it
And it sees right away that there is this wall of people that he can't go through
The guy on the right here is Marcos, He is holding the transmitter,he is not driving the robot but is holding the kill switch
And so
You know, that's what the the the convolutional net looks like
really small by today's standards
And
And it produces for every
every location every patch on the input
The second last layer is a 100 dimensional vector that goes into a classifier that classifies into five categories
so once the system classifies
Each of those five categories in the image you can you can warp the image
Into a map that's centered on the robot and you can you can do planning in this map to figure out like how to avoid
Obstacles and stuff like that. So this is what this thing does. It's a particular map called a hyperbolic map, but
It's not important for now
Now that
because this was you know
2007 the computers were slowly there were no GPUs so we could run this we could run this neural net only at about one frame per
second
As you can see here the at the bottom it updates about one frame per second
and
So if you have someone kind of walking in front of the robot the robot won't see it for a second and will you know?
Run over him
So that's why we have a second vision system here at the top. This one is stereo. It doesn't use a neural net
Odometry I think we don't care this is the controller which is also learned, but we don't care and
This is the the system here again, it's vision is crippled they can only see up to two point two and a half meters
So it's very short
But it kind of does a decent job
and
This is to test this sort of fast reacting vision systems or here pierre-simon a is jumping in front of it and
the robot stops right away so that now that's the full system with long-range vision and
annoying grad students
Right, so it's kind of giving up
Okay, oops
Okay, so
That's called semantic segmentation
But the real form of semantic segmentation is the one in which you you give an object category for every location
So that's the kind of problem here we're talking about where
every pixel is either building or sky or
Street or a car or something like this?
And around 2010 a couple datasets started appearing with a few thousand images where you could train vision systems to do this
And so the technique here is
essentially identical to the one I
Described it's also multi scale
So you basically have an input image you have a convolutional net
that has a set of outputs that you know, one for each category
Of objects for which you have label, which in this case is 33
When you back project one output of the convolutional net onto the input
It corresponds to an input window of 46 by 46 windows. So it's using a context of 46
by 46 pixels to make the decision about a single pixel at least that's the the
neural net at the back, at the bottom
But it has out 46 but 46 is not enough if you want to decide what a gray pixel is
Is it the shirt of the person is it the street? Is it the
Cloud or kind of pixel on the mountain. You have to look at a wider
context to be able to make that decision so
We use again this kind of multiscale approach where the same image is
Reduced by a factor of 2 and a factor of 4 and you run those two extra images to the same convolutional
net same weight same kernel same everything
Except the the last feature map you upscale them so that they have the same size as the original one
And now you take those combined feature Maps and send them to a couple layers of a classifier
So now the classifier to make its decision
Has four 46 by 46 windows on images that have been rescaled and so the effective
size of the context now is is 184 by 184 window because
the the core scale
Network basically looks at more this entire
Image
Then you can clean it up in various way I'm not gonna go to details for this but it works quite well
So this is the result
The guy who did this in my lab is Clément Farabet
He's a VP at Nvidia now in charge of all of machine learning infrastructure and the autonomous driving
Not surprisingly
And and so that system, you know, this is this is Washington Square Park by the way, so this is the NYU campus
It's not perfect far from that from that. You know it
Identified some areas of the street as sand
or desert and
There's no beach. I'm aware of in Washington Square Park
and
But you know
At the time this was the kind of system of this kind at the the number of training samples for this was very small
so it was kind of
It was about 2,000 or 3,000 images something like that
You run you take a you take a full resolution image
You run it to the first n minus 2 layers of your ConvNet that gives you your future Maps
Then you reduce the image by a factor of two run it again
You get a bunch of feature maps that are smaller then running again by reducing by a factor of four
You get smaller feature maps
now
You take the small feature map and you rescale it you up sample it so it's the same size as the first one same
for the second one, you stack all those feature maps together
Okay, and that you feed to two layers for a classifier for every patch
Yeah, the paper was rejected from CVPR 2012 even though the results were
record-breaking and
It was faster than the best competing
method by a factor of 50
Even running on standard hardware, but we also had implementation on special hardware that was incredibly fast
and
people didn't know what the convolutional net was at the time and so the reviewers basically could not fathom that
The method they'd never heard of could work
So well. There is way more to say about convolutional nets
But I encourage you to take a computer vision course for to hear about this
Yeah, this is okay this data set this particular dataset that we used
Is a collection of images street images that was collected mostly by Antonio Torralba at MIT and
He had a
sort of a tool for kind of labeling so you could you know, you could sort of
draw the contour over the object and then label of the object and
So if it would kind of, you know fill up the object most of the segmentations were done by his mother
Who's in Spain
she had a lot of time to
Spend doing this
Huh?
His mother yeah labeled that stuff. Yeah. This was in the late late 2000
Okay, now let's talk about a bunch of different architectures, right so
You know as I mentioned before
the idea of deep learning is that you have this catalog of modules that you can assemble in sort of different graphs and
and together to do different functions and
and a lot of the
Expertise in deep learning is to design those architectures to do something in particular
It's a little bit like, you know in the early days of computer science
Coming up with an algorithm to write a program was kind of a new concept
you know reducing a
Problem to kind of a set of instructions that could be run on a computer
It was kind of something new and here it's the same problem
you have to sort of imagine how to reduce a complex function into sort of a
graph possibly dynamic graph of
Functional modules that you don't need to know completely the function of but that you're going to whose function is gonna be finalized by learning
But the architecture is super important, of course
As we saw with convolutional Nets. the first important category is recurrent net. So
We've we've seen when we talked about the backpropagation
There's a big
Condition of the condition was that the graph of the interconnection of the module could not have loops. Okay. It had to be a
graph for which there is sort of at least a partial order of the module so that you can compute the
The the modules in such a way that when you compute the output of a module all of its inputs are available
But recurrent net is one in which you have loops
How do you deal with this?
So here is an example of a recurrent net architecture
Where you have an input which varies over time X(t) that goes through the first neural net. Let's call it an encoder
That produces a representation of the of the input
Let's call it H(t) and it goes into a recurrent layer
This recurrent layer is a function G that depends on trainable parameters W this trainable parameters also for the encoder
but I didn't mention it and
that
Recurrent layer takes into account H(t), which is the representation of the input
but it also takes into account Z(t-1), which is the
Sort of a hidden state, which is its output at a previous time step its own output at a previous time step
Okay, this G function can be a very complicated neural net inside
convolutional net whatever could be as complicated as you want. But what's important is that one of its inputs is
Its output at a previous time step
Okay
Z(t-1)
So that's why this delay indicates here. The input of G at time t is actually Z(t-1)
Which is the output its output at a previous time step
Ok, then the output of that recurrent module goes into a decoder which basically produces an output
Ok, so it turns a hidden representation Z into an output
So, how do you deal with this, you unroll the loop
So this is basically the same diagram, but I've unrolled it in time
Okay, so at time at times 0 I have X(0) that goes through the encoder produces H of 0 and then I apply
The G function I start with a Z arbitrary Z, maybe 0 or something
And I apply the function and I get Z(0) and that goes into the decoder produces an output
Okay
and then
Now that has Z(0) at time step 1. I can use the Z(0) as the previous output for the time step. Ok
Now the output is X(1) and time 1. I run through the encoder I run through the recurrent layer
Which is now no longer recurrent
And run through the decoder and then the next time step, etc
Ok, this network that's involved in time doesn't have any loops anymore
Which means I can run backpropagation through it
So if I have an objective function that says the last output should be that particular one
Or maybe the trajectory should be a particular one of the outputs. I
Can just back propagate gradient through this thing
It's a regular network with one
Particular characteristic, which is that every block
Shares the same weights
Okay, so the three instances of the encoder
They are the same encoder at three different time steps
So they have the same weights the same G functions has the same weights, the three decoders have the same weights. Yes
It can be variable, you know, I have to decide in advance
But it depends on the length of your input sequence
basically
Right and you know, it's you can you can run it for as long as you want
You know, it's the same weights over so you can just you know, repeat the operation
Okay this technique of unrolling and then back propagating through time basically is called surprisingly
BPTT back prop through time
It's pretty obvious
That's all there is to it
Unfortunately, they don't work very well at least not in their naive form
So in the naive form
So a simple form of recurrent net is one in which the encoder is linear
The G function is linear with high probably tangent or sigmoid or perhaps ReLU
And the decoder also is linear something like this maybe with a ReLU or something like that, right so it could be very simple
and
You get a number of problems with this and one problem is?
The so called vanishing gradient problem or exploding gradient problem
And it comes from the fact that if you have a long sequence, let's say I don't know 50 time steps
Every time you back propagate gradients
The gradients that get multiplied by the weight matrix of the G function. Okay at every time step
the gradients get multiplied by the the weight matrix now imagine the weight matrix has
small values in it
Which means that means that every time you take your gradient you multiply it by the transpose of this matrix to get the gradient at previous
time step
You get a shorter vector you get a smaller vector
And you keep rolling the the vector gets shorter and shorter exponentially
That's called the vanishing gradient problem by the time you get to the 50th
Time steps which is really the first time step. You don't get any gradient
Conversely if the weight matrix is really large and the non-linearity and your
Recurrent layer is not saturating
your gradients can explode if the weight matrix is large every time you multiply the
gradient by the transpose of the matrix
the vector gets larger and it explodes which means
your weights are going to diverge when you do a gradient step or you're gonna have to use a tiny learning rate for it to
work
So
You have to use a lot of tricks to make those things work
Here's another problem. The reason why you would want to use a recurrent net. Why would you want to use a recurrent net?
The purported advantage of recurrent net is that they can remember remember things from far away in the past
Okay
If for example you imagine that the the X's are our characters that you enter one by one
The characters come from I don't know a C program or something like that, right?
And
What your system is supposed to tell you at the end, you know?
it reads a few hundred characters corresponding to the source code of a function and at the end is
you want to train your system so that it produces one if it's a syntactically correct program and
Minus one if it's not okay
hypothetical problem
Recurrent Nets won't do it. Okay, at least not with our tricks
Now there is a thing here which is the issue which is that
Among other things this program has to have balanced braces and parentheses
So
It has to have a way of remembering how many open parentheses
there are so that it can check that you're closing them all or how many open braces there are so so all of them get
Get closed right so it has to store eventually, you know
Essentially within its hidden state Z
it has to store like how many braces and and
Parentheses were open if it wants to be able to tell at the end that all of them have been closed
So it has to have some sort of counter inside right
Yes
It's going to be a topic tomorrow
Now if the program is very long that means, you know Z has to kind of preserve information for a long time and
Recurrent net, you know give you the hope that maybe a system like this can do this, but because of a vanishing gradient problem
They actually don't at least not simple
Recurrent Nets
Of the type. I just described
So you have to use a bunch of tricks
Those are tricks from you know Yoshua Bengio's lab, but there is a bunch of them that were published by various people
Like Thomas Mikolov and various other people
So to avoid exploding gradients you can clip the gradients just you know, make it you know
If the gradients get too large, you just kind of squash them down
Just normalize them
Weak integration momentum I'm not gonna mention that. a good initialization so you want to initialize the weight matrices so that
They preserves the norm more or less
this is actually a whole bunch of papers on this on orthogonal neural nets and invertible
recurrent Nets
But the big trick is
LSTM and GRUs. Okay. So what is that before I talk about that I'm gonna talk about multiplicative modules
So what are multiplicative modules
They're basically
Modules in which you you can multiply things with each other
So instead of just computing a weighted sum of inputs you compute products of inputs and then weighted sum of that
Okay, so you have an example of this on the top left
on the top
so the output of a system here is just a weighted sum of
weights and inputs
Okay classic, but the weights actually themselves are weighted sums of weights and inputs
okay, so Wij here, which is the ij'th term in the weight matrix of
The module we're considering is actually itself
a weighted sum of
three third order tenser Uijk
weighted by variables Zk.
Okay, so basically what you get is that Wij is kind of a weighted sum of
Matrices
Uk
Weighted by a coefficient Zk and the Zk can change there are input variables the same way
So in effect, it's like having a neural net
With weight matrix W whose weight matrix is computed itself by another neural net
There is a general form of this where you don't just multiply matrices, but you have a neural net that is some complex function
turns X into S
Some generic function. Ok, give you ConvNet whatever and the weights of those neural nets
are not variables that you learn directly but they are the output of
Another neuron that that takes maybe another input into account or maybe the same input
Some people call those architectures hyper networks. Ok. There are networks whose weights are computed by another network
But here's just a simple form of it, which is kind of a bilinear form
or quadratic
form
Ok, so overall when you kind of write it all down
SI is equal to sum over j And k of Uijk Zk Xj. This is a double sum
People used to call this Sigma Pi units, yes
We'll come to this in just a second basically
If you want a neural net that can
perform a transformation from
A vector into another and that transformation is to be programmable
Right, you can have that transformation be computed by a neural net but the weight of that neural net would be it themselves the output
of
Another neural net that figures out what the transformation is
That's kind of the more general form more specifically is very useful if you want to route
Signals through a neural net in different ways on a data dependent way so
You in fact that's exactly what is mentioned below so the attention module is a special case of this
It's not a quadratic layer. It's kind of a different type, but it's a
particular type of
Architecture that
basically computes a
convex linear combination of a bunch of vectors, so
x₁ and x₂ here are vectors
w₁ and w₂ are scalars, basically, okay and
What the system computes here is a weighted sum of
x₁ and x₂ weighted by w₁ w₂ and again w₁ w₂ are scalars in this case
Here the sum at the output
so
Imagine that those two weights. w₁ w₂ are between 0 and 1 and sum to 1 that's what's called a convex linear combination
So by changing w₁ w₂ so essentially
If this sum to 1 there are the output of a softmax
Which means w₂ is equal to 1 - w₁ right? That's kind of the direct consequence
So basically by changing
the size of w₁ w₂ you kind of switch the output to
Being either x₁ or x₂ or some linear combination of the two some interpolation between the two
Okay
You can have more than just x₁ and x₂ you can have a whole bunch of x vectors
and that
system will basically choose an appropriate linear combination or focus
Is called an attention mechanism because it allows a neural net to basically focus its attention on a particular input and ignoring ignoring the others
The choice of this is made by another variable Z
Which itself could be the output to some other neural net that looks at Xs for example
okay, and
This has become a hugely important type of function, it's used in a lot of different situations now
In particular it's used in LSTM and GRU but it's also used in
Pretty much every natural language processing system nowadays that use
Either transformer architectures or all the types of attention they all use this kind of this kind of trick
Okay, so you have a vector Z pass it to a softmax
You get a bunch of numbers between 0 & 1 that sum to 1 use those as coefficient to compute a weighted sum
of a bunch of vectors X
xᵢ and you get the weighted sum
Weighted by those coefficients those coefficients are data dependent
Because Z is data dependent
All right, so
Here's an example of how you use this whenever you have this symbol here
This circle with the dots in the middle, that's a
Component by component multiplication of two vectors some people call this Hadamard product
Anyway, it's turn-by-turn multiplication. So this is a
a type of a kind of functional module
GRU, gated recurrent Nets, was proposed by Kyunghyun Cho who is professor here
And it attempts
It's an attempt at fixing the problem that naturally occur in
recurrent Nets that I mentioned the fact that you have exploding gradient the fact that the
recurrent nets don't really remember their states for very long. They tend to kind of forget really quickly
And so it's basically a memory cell
Okay, and I have to say this is the kind of second big family of sort of
Recurrent net with memory. The first one is LSTM, but I'm going to talk about it just afterwards
Just because this one is a little simpler
The equations are written at the bottom here so
basically, there is a
a
gating vector Z
which is
simply the application of a nonlinear function the sigmoid function
to
two linear layers and a bias and those two linear layers take into account the input X(t) and
The previous state which they did note H in their case, not Z like I did
Okay, so you take X you take H you compute matrices
You pass a result
you add the results you pass them through sigmoid functions and you get a bunch of
values between 0 & 1 because the sigmoid is between 0 & 1 gives you a coefficient and
You use those coefficients
You see the formula at the bottom the Z is used to basically compute a linear combination
of two inputs if Z is equal to 1
You basically only look at h(t-1). If Z
Is equal to 0 then 1 - Z is equal to 1 then you you look at this
expression here and
That expression is, you know some weight matrix multiplied by the input passed through a hyperbolic tangent function
It could be a ReLU but it's a hyperbolic tangent in this case
And it's combined with other stuff here that we can ignore for now
Okay. So basically what what the Z value does is that it tells the system just copy if Z equal 1 it just copies its
previous state and ignores the input
Ok, so it acts like a memory essentially. It just copies its previous state on its output
and if Z
Equals 0 then the current state is forgotten essentially and is basically you would you just read the input
Ok multiplied by some matrix so it changes the state of the system
Yeah, you do this component by component essentially, okay vector 1 yeah exactly
Well, it's just like the number of independent multiplications, right, what is the derivative of
some objective function with respect to the input of a product. It's equal to the
Derivative of that objective function with respect to the add, to the product multiplied by the other term. That's the as simple as that
So it's because by default
essentially unless Z is
your Z is
More less by default equal to one and so by default the system just copies its previous state
And if it's just you know slightly less than one it
It puts a little bit of the input into the state but doesn't significantly change the state and what that means. Is that it
preserves
Norm, and it preserves information, right?
Since basically memory cell that you can change continuously
Well because you need something between zero and one it's a coefficient, right
And so it needs to be between zero and one that's what we do sigmoids
I
mean you need one that is monotonic that goes between 0 and 1 and
is monotonic and differentiable I mean
There's lots of sigmoid functions, but you know
Why not?
Yeah, I mean there is some argument for using others, but you know doesn't make a huge
amount of difference
Okay in the full form of gru. there is also a reset gate. So the reset gate is
Is this guy here? So R is another vector that's computed also as a linear combination of inputs and previous state and
It serves to multiply the previous state. So if R is 0 then the previous state is
if R is 0 and Z is 1
The system is basically completely reset to 0 because that is 0
So it only looks at the input
But that's basically a simplified version of something that came out way earlier in 1997 called
LSTM long short-term memory
Which you know attempted
Which was an attempt at solving the same issue that you know recurrent Nets basically lose memory for too long
and so you build them as
As memory cells by default and by default they will preserve the information
It's essentially the same idea here
It's a you know, the details are slightly different here don't have dots in the middle of the round shape here for the product
But it's the same thing
And there's a little more kind of moving parts. It's basically it looks more like an actual run sale
So it's like a flip-flop they can you know preserve
Information and there is some leakage that you can have, you can reset it to 0 or to 1
It's fairly complicated
Thankfully people at NVIDIA Facebook Google and various other places have very efficient implementations of those so you don't need to
figure out how to write the
CUDA code for this or write the back pop
Works really well
it's it's quite what you'd use but it's used less and less because
people use recurrent Nets
people used to use recurrent Nets for natural language processing
mostly and
Things like speech recognition and speech recognition is moving towards using convolutional Nets
temporal conditional Nets
while the natural language processing is moving towards using what's called transformers
Which we'll hear a lot about tomorrow, right?
no?
when
two weeks from now, okay
So what transformers are
Okay, I'm not gonna talk about transformers just now
but these key transformers are kind of a generalization so
General use of attention if you want
So the big neural Nets that use attention that you know
Every block of neuron uses attention and that tends to work pretty well it works
So well that people are kind of basically dropping everything else for NLP
so the problem is
Systems like LSTM are not very good at this so
Transformers are much better. The biggest transformers have billions of parameters
Like the biggest one is by 15 billion something like that that order of magnitude the t5 or whatever it's called
from Google so
That's an enormous amount of memory and it's because of the particular type of architecture that's used in transformers
They they can actually store a lot of knowledge if you want
So that's the stuff people would use for
What you're talking about like question answering systems
Translation systems etc. They will use transformers
Okay
So because LSTM kind of was sort of you know one of the first
architectures recurrent architecture that kind of worked
People tried to use them for things that at first you would think are crazy but turned out to work
And one example of this is translation. It's called neural machine translation
So there was a paper
by Ilya Sutskever at NIPS 2014 where he
Trained this giant multi-layer LSTM. So what's a multi-layered LSTM? It's an LSTM where you have
so it's the unfolded version, right? So at the bottom here you have an LSTM which is here unfolded for three time steps
But it will have to be unfolded for the length of a sentence you want to translate, let's say a
sentence in French
and
And then you take the hidden
state at every time step of this LSTM and you feed that as input to a second LSTM and
I think in his network
he actually had four layers of that so you can think of this as a
Stacked LSTM that you know each of them are recurrent in time
But they are kind of stacked as the layers of a neural net
so
At the last time step in the last layer, you have a vector here, which is meant to represent the entire meaning of that sentence
Okay, so it could be a fairly large vector
and then you feed that to another multi-layer LSTM, which
You know you run for a sort of undetermined number of steps and
The role of this LSTM is to produce words in a target language if you do translation say German
Okay, so this is time, you know
It takes the state you run through the first two layers of the LSTM
Produce a word and then take that word and feed it as input to the next time step
So that you can generate text sequentially, right?
Run through this produce another word take that word feed it back to the input and keep going. So this is a
Should do this for translation you get this gigantic
Neural net you train and this is the it's a system of this type
The one that Sutskever represented at NIPS 2014 it was was the first neural
Translation system that had performance that could rival sort of more classical approaches not based on neural nets
And people were really surprised that you could get such results
That success was very short-lived
Yeah, so the problem is
The word you're gonna say at a particular time depends on the word you just said
Right, and if you ask the system to just produce a word
And then you don't feed that word back to the input
the system could be used in other word that has that is inconsistent with the previous one you produced
It should but it doesn't
I mean not well enough that that it works. So so this is so this is kind of sequential production is pretty much required
In principle, you're right
It's not very satisfying
so there's a problem with this which is that the entire meaning of the sentence has to be kind of squeezed into
That hidden state that is between the encoder of the decoder
That's one problem the second problem is that despite the fact that that LSTM are built to preserve information
They are basically memory cells. They don't actually preserve information for more than about 20 words
So if your sentence is more than 20 words by the time you get to the end of the sentence
Your your hidden state will have forgotten the beginning of it
so what people use for this the fix for this is a huge hack is called BiLSTM and
It's a completely trivial idea that consists in running two LSTMs in opposite directions
Okay, and then you get two codes one that is
running the LSTM from beginning to end of the sentence that's one vector and then the second vector is from
Running an LSTM in the other direction you get a second vector. That's the meaning of your sentence
You can basically double the length of your sentence without losing too much information this way, but it's not a very satisfying solution
So if you see biLSTM, that's what that's what it is
So as I said, the success was short-lived because in fact before the paper was published at NIPS
There was a paper by
Dzmitry Bahdanau, Kyunghyun Cho and Yoshua Bengio
which was published on arxiv in September 14 that said
We can use attention. So the attention mechanism I mentioned earlier
Instead of having those gigantic
Networks and squeezing the entire meaning of a sentence into this small vector
it would make more sense to the translation if
Every time said, you know, we want to produce a word in French corresponding to a sentence in English
If we looked at the location in the English sentence that had that word
Okay
so
Our decoder is going to produce french words one at a time and when it comes to produce a word
that has an equivalent in the input english sentence it's
going to focus its attention on that word and then the translation from French to English of that word would be simple or the
You know, it may not be a single word
it could be a group of words right because
Very often you have to turn a group of word in English into a group of words in French to kind of say the same
thing if it's German you have to
put the
You know the verb at the end of the sentence whereas in English, it might be at the beginning
So basically you use this attention mechanism
so this attention module here is the one that I showed a couple slides earlier which basically decides
Which of the time steps which of the hidden representation for which other word in the input sentence it is going to focus on
To kind of produce a representation that is going to produce the current word at a particular time step
So here we're at time step number three, we're gonna produce a third word
And we're gonna have to decide which of the input word corresponds to this and we're gonna have this attention mechanism
so essentially we're gonna have a
Small piece of neural net that's going to look at the the inputs on this side
It's going to have an output which is going to go through a soft max that is going to produce a bunch of
Coefficients that sum to 1 between 0 and 1 and they're going to compute a linear combination of the states at different time steps
Ok by setting one of those coefficients to 1 and the other ones to 0 it is going to focus the attention of the system on
one particular word
So the magic of this is that this neural net that decides that runs to the softmax and decides on those coefficients actually
Can be trained with back prop is just another
Set of weights in a neural net and you don't have to built it by hand. It just figures it out
This completely revolutionized the field of neural machine translation in the sense that
within a
Few months team from Stanford won a big competition with this beating all the other methods
And then within three months every big company that works on translation had basically deployed systems based on this
So this just changed everything
And then people started paying attention to attention, okay pay more attention to attention in a sense that
And then there was a paper by a bunch of people at Google
What the title was attention is all you need and It was basically a paper that solved a bunch of natural language processing tasks
by using a neural net where every layer, every group of neurons basically was implementing attention and that's what a
Or something called self attention. That's what a transformer is
Yes, you can have a variable number of outputs of inputs that you focus attention on
Okay, I'm gonna talk now about memory networks
So this stems from work at Facebook that was started by Antoine Bordes
I think in 2014 and
By
Sainbayar Sukhbaatar, I
Think in 2015 or 16
Called end-to-end memory networks
Sainbayar Sukhbaatar was a PhD student here and it was an intern at Facebook when he worked on this
together with a bunch of other people Facebook and
the idea of memory
Network is that you'd like to have a short-term memory you'd like your neural net to have a short-term memory or working memory
Okay, you'd like it to you know, you you tell okay, if I tell you a story I tell you
John goes to the kitchen
John picks up the milk
Jane goes to the kitchen
And then John goes to the bedroom and drops the milk there
And then goes back to the kitchen and ask you. Where's the milk? Okay
so every time I had told you a sentence you kind of
updated in your mind a
Kind of current state of the world if you want
and so by telling you the story you now you have a representation of the state to the world and if I ask you a
Question about the state of the world you can answer it. Okay
You store this in a short-term memory
You didn't store it, ok, so there's kind of this
There's a number of different parts in your brain, but it's two important parts, one is the cortex
The cortex is where you have long term memory. Where you
You know you
Where all your your thinking is done and all that stuff and there is a separate
You know
Chunk of neurons called the hippocampus which is sort of
Its kind of two formations in the middle of the brain and they kind of send
Wires to pretty much everywhere in the cortex and
The hippocampus is thought that to be used as a short-term memory. So it can just you know, remember things for relatively short time
The prevalent
theory is that when you when you sleep and you dream there's a lot of information that is being transferred from your
hippocampus to your cortex to be solidified in long-term memory
Because the hippocampus has limited capacity
When you get senile like you get really old very often your hippocampus shrinks and
You don't have short-term memory anymore. So you keep repeating the same stories to the same people
Okay, it's very common
Or you go to a room to do something and by the time you get to the room you forgot what you were there for
This starts happening by the time you're 50, by the way
So, I don't remember what I said last week of two weeks ago, um
Okay, but anyway, so memory network, here's the idea of memory network
You have an input to the memory network. Let's call it X and think of it as an address
Of the memory, okay
What you're going to do is you're going to compare this X
With a bunch of vectors, we're gonna call K
So k₁ k₂ k₃
Okay, so you compare those two vectors and the way you compare them is via dot product very simple
Okay, so now you have the three dot products of all the three Ks with the X
They are scalar values, you know plug them to a softmax
So what you get are three numbers between 0 & 1 that sum to 1
What you do with those you have 3 other vectors that I'm gonna call V
v₁, v₂ and v₃
And what you do is you multiply
These vectors by those scalars, so this is very much like the attention mechanism that we just talked about
Okay, and you sum them up
Okay, so take an X compare X with each of the K each of the Ks those are called keys
You get a bunch of coefficients between the zero and one that sum to one and then compute a linear combination of the values
Those are value vectors
And
Sum them up
Okay, so imagine that one of the key exactly matches X you're gonna have a large coefficient here and small coefficients there
So the output of the system will essentially be V2, if K 2 matches X the output would essentially be V 2
Okay
So this is an addressable associative memory
Associative memory is exactly that where you have keys with values and if your input matches a key you get the value here
It's a kind of soft differentiable version of that
So you can
you can back propagate to this you can you can write into this memory by changing the V vectors or
Even changing the K vectors. You can change the V vectors by gradient descent
Okay, so if you wanted the output of the memory to be something in particular by backpropagating gradient through this
you're going to change the currently active V to whatever it needs for the
for the output
So in those papers
What what they did was I
Mean there's a series of papers on every network, but
What they did was exactly scenario I just explained where you you kind of
Tell a story to a system so give it a sequence of sentences
Those sentences are encoded into vectors by running through a neural net which is not pre-trained, you know
it just through the training of the entire system it figures out how to encode this
and then those sentences are written to the memory of this type and
Then when you ask a question to the system you encode the question at the input of a neural net, the neural net produces
An X to the memory the memory returns a value
And
Then you use this value
and the previous state of the network to kind of reaccess the memory, you can do this multiple times and
You train this entire network to produce or an answer to your to your question
And if you have lots and lots of scenarios lots and lots of questions or also lots of answers
Which they did in this case with by artificially generating stories questions and answers
this thing actually
learns to store stories and
answer questions
Which is pretty amazing
So that's the memory Network
Okay, so the first step is you compute
Alpha I equals
KI transpose X. Okay, just a dot product. Okay, and then you compute
CI or the vector C I should say
Is the softmax function
Applied to the vector of alphas, okay
So the C's are between 0 and 1 and sum to 1 and then the output of the system
is
sum over I of
Ci
Vi where Vis are the value vectors. Okay. That's the memory
Yes, yes, yes, absolutely
Not really
No, I mean all you need is everything to be encoded as vectors?
Right and so run for your favorite convnet, you get a vector that represents the image and then you can do the QA
Yeah, I mean so
You can imagine lots of applications of this so in particular
When application is I
Mean you can you can think of
You know think of this as a kind of a memory
And then you can have some sort of neural net
That you know
it takes takes an input and then produces an address for the memory gets a value back and
Then keeps growing and eventually produces an output
This was very much like a computer
Ok. Well the neural net here is the
the CPU the ALU the CPU
Ok, and the memory is just an external memory you can access whenever you need it, or you can write to it if you want
It's a recurrent net in this case. You can unfold it in time, which is what these guys did
And
And then so then there are people who kind of imagined that you could actually build kind of differentiable computers out of this
There's something called neural Turing machine, which is essentially a form of this where the memory is not of this type
It's kind of a soft tape like in a regular Turing machine
This is somewhere from deep mind that the interesting story about this which is that the facebook people put out
The paper on the memory network on arxiv and three days later
The deepmind people put out a paper
About neural Turing machine and the reason they put three days later is that they've been working on the all Turing machine and
in their
Tradition they kind of keep project secret unless you know until they can make a big splash
But there they got scooped so they put the paper out on arxiv
Eventually, they made a big splash with another with a paper but that was a year later or so
So what's happened
since then is that people have kind of taken this module this idea that you compare inputs to keys and
that gives you coefficients and
You know you you produce values
as
Kind of a essential module in a neural net and that's basically where the transformer is
so a transformer is basically a neural net in which
Every group of neurons is one of those
It's a it's a whole bunch of memories. Essentially. There's some more twist to it. Okay, but that's kind of the basic the basic idea
But you'll hear about this
in a week Oh
in two weeks
one week one week
Okay any more questions?
Cool. All right. Thank you very much